Guide to the Student Newspapers Collection Student newspaper publications of the Danbury Normal School, Danbury Teachers College, Danbury State Teachers College, Western Connecticut State College and Western Connecticut State University RG 5.15.1
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Student Newspapers Collection.
1931-2002
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Western Connecticut State University
RG 5.15.1
147
26 Linear Feet 17 boxes
The collection includes newspapers published by student through the history of Western Connecticut State University and its institutional antecedents.
Provenance
Ongoing transfer to the University Archives.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Western Connecticut State University (WCSU) student newspaper went through several incarnations before it became The Echo in 1955.
The oldest surviving student "newspaper" dates from October 16, 1931. However, the masthead indicates that this was the first issue of the eighth volume of Dee N Ess (phonetic spelling for "DNS" -Danbury Normal School) and was a mimeographed publication more akin to a newsletter. It may be that the first issues were published in the early 1920s. The publication contained campus news, student writings (essays and poetry primarily), comics, and artwork. In 1936, the Danbury Normal School became the Danbury Teachers' College. The newspaper reflected the changes taking place at the school by changing its name in the fall of 1936. Dee Tee Cee continued Dee N Ess. In 1941, the name changed again to Campus Crier. The Archives does not have any copies of newspapers from 1942 through the spring of 1944. This may be due to the fact that student organizations curtailed their activities during the war years. In March of 1944, the student newspaper reemerged, this time under the name: The Inkling. The Inkling took on a more professional look, was typeset and contained photographs.
In 1948 when the college adopted a new constitution and emerged as the Danbury State Teachers' College, the student paper repositioned itself again as The Courier. This was another step toward becoming a more professional publication and, for a while, it even adopted the more traditional newspaper-style tabloid format. However, The Courier evolved into a more literary publication and in the spring of 1953 a group of students started publishing a second newspaper, The Supplement. It operated as a more informal but carried on with more student-newspaper-like content than The Courier.
In 1955 The Supplement took on a new and enduring moniker: The Echo. From November 23, 1955 to the present, this has been the primary student newspaper for the university.
Scope and Content Note
Of interest is the final May 1936 issue of Dee N Ess that contains a foreword written by the school's president, Ralph C. Jenkins, entitled "What's In a Name?" In the piece, President Jenkins discussed the meaning of the word "normal" in the school's title and its implications for the school's mission. It was at this time that the school's name changed to Danbury Teachers' College. The newspaper reflected the changes taking place at the school by changing its name in the fall of 1936.
Volume and issue numbering is inconsistent throughout the first twenty-year-run of the newspapers. Volume numbers stop and start at random and the number of a particular issue is sometimes duplicated or left off all together.
As of the first publication of The Echo in 1955, issue and volume numbering is normalized, and the Archives holds a complete set. Issues after 2002 have not been processed but the Archives holds copies.
Arrangement
Folders are chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into 1 series.
Missing Title
Inventory
Newspapers.; Universities and colleges.; College students.; Teachers colleges.; Newsletters.; Publications.; Danbury (Conn.); Universities and colleges -- United States -- Newspapers -- History.; Jenkins, Ralph Carlton, 1891-; Western Connecticut State University -- History.; Western Connecticut State College -- History.; Danbury State Tearchers College -- History.; Danbury Normal School -- History.; Danbury Teachers College -- History.
- Inventory, 42054
  - Dee N Ess, March 1926, 42094 (Box 1)
    General
    Formation of the Student Cooperation Plan; student events and trips.
    Scope and Contents
    First issue of Dee N Ess dated March 25, 1926, Vol. II, No. 27.
  - Dee N Ess, October 1931 through May 1936, 1931-1936; 42093 (Box 1)
    Missing Issues:
    March 18, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 22 to April 30, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 27
    May 27, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 31 to September 16, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 19
    December 16, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 14
    January 20, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 18
    March 3, 1933 Vol. 9, No. 24 to March 17, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 26.
    April 14, 1933, Vol 9, No. 30 to November 8, 1933, Vol. 10, No. 7
    November 29, 1933, Vol. 10, No. 9
    January 3, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 12
    January 24, 1934, Vol 10, No. 15
    February 21, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 19
    February 28, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 20
    March 13, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 21
    April 10, 1935, Vol 11. No. 25 - May 1935, Vol. 11, No. ?
    September 1935, Vol. 12, No. 1 - November 13, 1935, Vol. 12, No. 6
    November 27, 1935, Vol. 12, No. 8
    February 9, 1936, Vol 12, No. 16
    February 16, 1936, Vol. 12, No. 17
    March 11, 1936, Vol. 12, No. 18 - May 6, 1936, Vol. 12, No. 27
    Articles missing from the following issues:
    November 4, 1932 November 18, 1932 December 9, 1932 January 8, 1936
    October 16, 1931, Vol 8, Number 1 Student activities; Club and Alumnae Notes; the Forum's first meeting of the year; and poetry by Florence Stoll.
    October 23, 1931, Vol 8, Number 2 The DeeNeeS is published by a new senior division each month; "The Forum Asks" Personals; Alumnae, Faculty, and Club notes.
    October 30, 1931, Vol 8, Number 3 International news; "The Forum Suggests;" Club and Alumnae Notes; Personals; student poetry.
    November 11, 1918, Vol 8, Number 4 Cover illustration entitled "Le Wagon du Marechal Foch, The car in which the Armistice was signed November 11, 1918," by A.L.T: Club Notes; Personals; first mention of Student Council; "The Forum" Notes.
    November 13, 1931, Vol 8, Number 5 Club and Alumnae Notes, The Forum Column, and Personals.
    November 20, 1931, Vol. 8, Number 6 Club activities, Assembly Notes; The Forum Column; Governor Cross visits Danbury for Armistice day; poetry, and Personals.
    November 25, 1931, Vol. 8, Number 7 Club activities; Personals; students visit New York City.
    December 4, 1931, Vol. 8, Number 8 Junior and senior volleyball; Club Notes; The Forum Column; and Personals.
    December 11, 1931, Vol. 8, Number 9 Dr. Ambroso L. Suhric, head of the Teacher Training Department of NYU visits DNS; The Forum Column; students and faculty attend luncheon given by Connecticut Secondary Schools Society of Internation Cooperation at New Haven and hear Sir Wilfred Grenfell speak on foreign affairs; varsity-faculty volleyball; and poetry.
    December 18, 1931, Vol. 8, Number 10 Training School Notes, Alumnae and Club Notes; The Forum Column; and, Personals.
    December 23, 1931, Vol. 8, No. 11 Dramatic Club presents a Christmas play "When the Chimes Rang;" Club Notes, The Forum Column.
    January 8, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 12 Annual conference of the Connecticut Normal School faculty members held in New Haven; International news; Faculty and Club Notes; and, student poetry.
    January 13, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 13 Formal dance planned by the Social Committee; Dr. James E. Rogers speaks at special assembly; Club Notes; series of assemblies planned to observe the bicentennial; The Forum Column.
    January 22, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 14 Cover illustration of Benjamin Franklin entitled "Beware of little expenses, a small leak will sink a great ship." Assembly programs; Club and Hall Notes; The Forum Column; and, student poetry.
    January 29, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 15 Assembly hosts Miss Kiely, Principal of the Bridgeport City Normal School; Hall Notes; sports; Club News; The Forum Column; student poetry.
    February 5, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 16 Cover illustration of world entitled "Forum Dinner" by A.M.M. Forum Radio Committee formed; Forum guest speaker Mr. C. Douglas Booth of the Royal Institute of International Affairs in England; The Forum column; Club and Faculty Notes; Hall and Locust Avenue Notes.
    February 11, 1932, Vol. 8 No. 17 Cover illustration "LINCOLN, an Apostle of Freedom, and a lover of peace." Forum speaker D.Douglas Booth; The Forum Column; Faculty, Hall, Balmforth Avenue Notes.
    February 19, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 18 Dramatic Club will present "The Rector" by Rachel Cruthers, and "The Obstinate Family." Club news, Faculty Notes; Locust Avenue and Balmforth Avenue notes; The Forum Column; poetry by Gladys Fishelberg.
    February 26, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 19 Club notes; alumnae weekend; The Forum Column; poetry by Gladys Fishelberg.
    March 4, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 20 Alumnae weekend; Faculty and Club Notes; Athletic Association news; The Forum Column.
    March 11, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 21 Alumnae weekend; statesman Aristide Briand dies; Club and Hall Notes; The Forum Column.
    May 6, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 28 New column introduced "The Inquisitive Reporter;" Assembly program; Faculty, Hall, and Club Notes; The Forum Column; poetry by Gladys Fishelberg.
    May 13, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 29 Club, Faculty, Hall, and Assembly Notes; Dramatic Club presents "A Dish of China Tea" and "At Candlelight Time" for the benefit of the PTA of both rural schools; The Forum Column; The Inquisitive Reporter.
    May 20, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 30 Club and Hall Notes; The Forum Column; Training Notes; and, poetry by Gladys E.Fishelberg.
    May 27, 1932, Vol. 8, No. 31 George Washington pageant by the children of Balmforth Avenue School; Assembly, Clubs; Hall News and Notes; The Inquisitive Reporter.
    September 16, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 1 Club News, The Forum Column; Faculty Notes; First Days at D.N.S.; Coming Events.
    September 23, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 2 Club News and Notes; Assembly Notes; Faculty-Student Reception; Britian Condemns German Arms Plea.
    September 30, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 3 Dr. Ernest Butterfield, Commissioner of Education to speak; "Great Britain Relents, Gandhi Ends His Fast;" Clubs, Assembly, and Faculty Notes; The Forum Column.
    October 6, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 4 Clubs, Assembly, Social, Faculty Notes; and, The Forum Column.
    October 14, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 5 Assembly, Faculty, and Club Notes; The Forum Column; and, Social Notes.
    October 21, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 6 The Forum Column by Frances Hamm and Ann Cronin, Faculty, Assembly, and Club Notes.
    October 27, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 7 Faculty, Social and Club Notes; and, The Forum Column by Frances Hamm and Ann Cronin.
    November 4, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 8 The Forum at Wesleyan; Club News; volleyball; Personals; The Forum Column by Irene Coughlin, Catherine Magner, and Adelaide Starr; Dramatic Club presents "Part Time Job."
    November 10, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 9 Faculty, Hall, and Assembly Notes, Club News; The Forum Column; and poetry by Fannie Teichholz.
    November 18, 1932, Vol 9, No. 10 Faculty Notes; Club Notes; Personals; The Forum Column; poetry by Ruth Miller and Mary Wrenn.
    November 23, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 11 Assembly Notes, Club news; The Forum Column; Personals; Faculty Notes; and, poetry by Fannie Teichholz and Mary Wrenn.
    December 2, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 12 Club News and Notes; The Forum Column; Faculty Notes, Personals; and, student poetry.
    December 9, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 13 December meeting of the Danbury League of Women Voters held at DNS; The Forum travels to Yale to hear Dr. Julius Curtuis on "Germany and Disarmament;" Poetry by Ellen Hunt.
    December 21, 1932, Vol. 9, No. 15 Assembly and Faculty Notes; The Origins of Christmas; Forum Notes; Athletic Association gives a party.
    January 6, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 16 Dramatic Club will present "Between Trains" and "Her Uncle's Boots." The Forum Column; Clubs News and Notes; Personals; Alumnae News; Faculty Notes; poetry by Mary Wrenn.
    January 13, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 17 Review of Dramatic Club's two one-act plays; Assembly, Faculty and Club Notes; The Forum Column; Philippine Independence discussed.
    January 27, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 19 Mrs. Marietta Johnson of the Fairhope School in Fairhope, Alabama, speaks of the founding of the school; League of Nations questions Japan on Mandates; The Forum Column; Faculty and Assembly Notes.
    February 3, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 20 Death of two authors: Sara Teasdale and John Galsworthy; Assembly, Club and Faculty Notes; Forum Reports; Personals
    February 10, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 21 Lothrop Higgins addressed the first February meeting of The Forum; The Forum Column; Faculty and Assembly Notes; Personals.
    February 17, 1933, Vol. 9. No. 22 The Forum Column, Club News and Notes; Faculty Notes; Sports; poetry by Fannie Teichholz.
    February 24, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 23 Club News and Notes; The Forum Reports; Faculty and Hall Notes.
    March 24, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 27 Assembly and Club Notes; new faculty at Balmforth Avenue School; thoughts on Education and Depression; Hall Notes; The Forum Column.
    March 31, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 28 "Will Danbury Normal School Close?" Dramatic Club speaker Madame Ortmann, German opera star; Faculty, Assembly, Club, and Hall Notes; Forum Column.
    April 7, 1933, Vol. 9, No. 29 Forum to hold dinner, Dr. James T. Shotwell, professor of history at Columbia University, to speak; Clubs News; Assembly and Hall Notes; Forum Column; poetryby Alice C. Wight and Gertrude Baughan.
    November 15, 1933, Vol. 10, No. 7 Special Features on Art and Music by Edith Vogel, Assistant Editor; Assembly and Forum notes; Personals.
    November 22, 1933, Vol. 10, No. 8 Women's Basketball; Beacon Hill Symphonic Ensemble performed at Danbury High School Auditorium; Club news; Personals; poetry by Inez Whitworth; book reviews on "Mild Oats" by Florence Ryerson and Colin Clemonts, and "San Michele" by Axel Munthe.
    December 6, 1933, Vol. 10, No. 10 DNS students attend "University in Exile" seminar at the New School for Social Research; Alumnae Association sponor camp project; Forum News.
    December 13, 1933, Vol. 10, No. 11 Forum members attend League of Nations Dinner in New Haven; Divisions to sponsor teas; Alumnae and Club News; comments on Prof. Brandt's lecture on peasant life in Europe and Asia.
    January 10, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 13 Club news; personals; concert news; Commercial Students wish everyone a successful year.
    January 17, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 14 Assembly news; basketball, Forum and Club news; Faculty Notes.
    January 31, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 16 Formal dance held at Fairfield Hall; Assembly Notes; Club, Forum, and Faculty News.
    February 7, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 17 Mr. Higgins addresses Nature Club; Assembly Notes; Faculty and Weekend News.
    February 14, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 18 Assembly to commemorate the anniversary of President Lincoln's birth; Club news; Faculty News, Over The Week-End (personals); Tributes to Lincoln.
    March 7, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 21 Hitler Seeks Vienna Peace; Assembly News; Personals.
    March 14, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 22 Assembly Notes; Personals; Faculty News; poetry by Ella Wheeler Wilcox.
    March 21, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 23 Walter B. Spencer, principal of New Haven Commercial High School, addresses business students; Dramatic Club will present "St. Cecelina" and "Up in the Air." Assembly and club notes; Faculty News; Forum students quiz Mr. Albert Walsh, first selectman of the Town of Danbury.
    March 28, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 24 The history of Easter; Assembly Notes; Principal of Waterbury High School addresses DNS students; Club activities; Faculty News; Personals; Review of John Masefield's "Bird of Dawning."
    April 11, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 25 Social Committee entertains with a Bridge-Tea; Assembly Notes; Faculty News; "Snoops-----or Scoops" column.
    April 18, 1934, Vol 10, No. 26 Forum Banquet speakers Lothrop Higgins and Dr. Schuyler Wallace; Assembly Notes; Club activities; Personals; advice to freshmen.
    April 23, 1934, Vol. 10, No. 27 Forum Banquet; Club Activities; Normal School Camp; Assembly Notes; News of the Training Schools (Locust Avenue and Balmforth Avenue).
    October 3, 1934, Vol. 11, No. 1 Freshman welcomed at reception; Danbury Fair; Editorial on Christopher Columbus; Book Review on "The Testament Of Youth" by Vera Brittain; Alumnae and Assembly Notes; Faculty News; Club activities; NewsFlashes; Spices column.
    October 10, 1934, Vol. 11, No. 2 Spanish Socialist Revolt; Nobel Peace Prize; Book Review on "As The Earth Turns" by Gladys Hasty Carrol; Assembly Notes; Editorial; Spices and Music Columns.
    October 17, 1934, Vol 11, No. 3 Alumnae and Faculty Notes; Clubs News; Editorial Column; Book Review on "Stars Fell On Alabama" by Carl Carmer; Dramatic Club sponsors visit by Nancy Byrd Turner, poetess; Last Complimentary Issue of the DeeNesS.
    October 24,1934, Vol. 11, No. 4 Annual Play Day of the four Normal Schools and Connecticut State College; Editorial "Keep Young;" Assembly and Club News; Book Review on "Twenty Years A Growing" by Maurice O'Sullivan; Faculty and Alumnae Notes.
    October 31, 1934, Vol 11, No. 5 Senior C Division hold Bridge-Tea; Faculty Notes; Book review on "42 Years in the White House" by Irvin H. (Ike) Hoover; Personals; Library Committee Party; Coming Events.
    November 7, 1934, Vol 11, No. 6 Forum sponsors lecturers on Russia, Augusta Sutton first speaker; Assembly, Faculty, and Alumnae Notes; Book Review on "The Sea Hawk" by Rafael Sabatini; Coming Attractions; "Through the Keyhole" Column.
    November 15, 1934, Vol. 11, No. 7 International Peace Program, The Family of Nations, reviewed; Faculty, Alumnae, Assembly and Club Notes; Coming Attractions Column; Personals; Book review on "Wine From These Grapes" by Edna St. Vincent Millay.
    November 21, 1934, Vol 11, No. 8 Forum sponsors lecturers on Russia, Augusta Sutton second speaker; Assembly, Alumnae, Faculty Notes; Book review on "The Book That Nobody Knows" by Bruce Barton; "Through the Keyhole" column; Coming Attractions Column; student poetry.
    November 28, 1934, Vol 11, No. 9 Forum sponsors lecturers on Russia, Augusta Sutton third speaker; Club news; Book review on "Without My Cloak" by Kate O'Brien; Assembly and Faculty Notes; Personals; Social Committee Column.
    December 5, 1934, Vol 11, No. 10 World News; Mr. and Mrs. Higgins attend student Thanksgiving celebration in Fairfield Hall; Book review on "The House in the Hills" by Simmone Ratel; Assembly News; Students visit Town Farm; Personals.
    December 12, 1934, Vol 11, No. 11 World News; Annual Senior Kiddie Party; Locust Avenue School sponsors bazaar; Coming Events column; Assembly and Club news; Personals; Book review on "Lamb in His Bosom" by Caroline Miller.
    December 18, 1934, Vol 11, No. 12 Labor news; August Sutton speaker at Connecticut branch of the League of Nations Association; Assembly News; Glee Club operetta; Miry Brook entertainment; Social Committe notes; books for vacation reading; student poetry.
    January 9, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 13 International News entitled "An Anxious World Is Waiting;" Visits to Town Farm encouraged; January 3 Assembly speaker Mr. Higgins spoke on world affairs; Dramatic Club presented "The Cancelled Debt" on December 20, 1934; Faculty and Training School News; Club News; Personals.
    January 16, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 14 International News entitled "New Friendships;" Assembly and Club News; Faculty News; Coming Events; Personals.
    January 23, 1935, Vol 11, No. 15 Forum speaker Mr. E. Ward Ireland, Superintendent of Schools in Stratford, discusses "Education;" Assembly and Club Notes and Personals; article entitled "An International Issue in the New Deal;" Book review on "An Altar In The Fields" by Ludwig Lewisohn; Faculty News.
    January 30, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 16 Editorial Staff listed; Forum speaker Leon C. Staples, Superintendent of Schools in Stamford, urges school leadership; Assembly Notes; Club and Faculty Notes, Personals; Book review on "Another Caesar" by Alfred Newman.
    February 6, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 17 DNS Library supplemented by pay collection of recent outstanding books; Club and Assembly Notes; "The Story of the Schaghticokes;" Faculty Notes and Personals; Book review on "The Taking of the Gry" by John Masefield; student poetry.
    February 13, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 18 Assembly and Club Notes; Highlights on Nearby Towns; Faculty Notes; Personals; Book review on "Road To Ages" by Robert Nathan.
    February 20, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 19 Rural Club speaker James R. Case discusses some of the problems encountered in working with youth, particularly in the 4-H Clubs; Assembly and Club Notes; Coming Events; Faculty Notes; Personals; Book review on "Matador" by Marguerite Steen.
    February 27, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 20 "Twelfth Night" presented by the Edgerow Theater Players of Rose Valley, PA; Forum to resume Sunday night speakers; Book review on "The Old Man Dies" by Elizabeth Spriggs; Personals; Faculty News.
    March 20, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 22 Progressive Education Convention and Scholastic Press Convention attended by DNS students; Memoriam for Lothrop D. Higgins; Assembly Notes on European nations; Club Notes; Coming Events; Personals; Faculty News.
    March 27, 1935, Vol. 11, No. 23 Dramatic Club presents "The Obstinate Family" and "Will-O' the Wisp;" Faculty, Assembly and Club Notes; Personals; Book reviews on "Of Time and the River" by Thomas Wolfe and "What Price Mallorca;" student poetry.
    April 3, 1935, Vol 11, No. 24 Anthony "Eden's Week of Travels;" Assembly Notes; Club News; The Forum Column; Coming Events; Faculty News; "A Story With Names" by Evelyn Luciano.
    November 20, 19325, Vol. 12, No. 7 Editorial Staff listed; Forum speaker Dr. Goodwin Watson of Columbia University discusses "Building a New America;" Coming Events; Club News; Personals.
    December 4, 1935, Vol 12, No. 9 Editorial Staff listed; Coming Events; Personals; Assembly news; Book review on "Manners for Millions" by Sophie C. Hadida.
    December 11, 1935, Vol. 12, No. 10 Forum delegates attend Foreign Policy Association meeting in New York, and the League of Nations Association annual meeting in Hartford; DNS attends New England English Teachers' Convention; Coming Events; Editorial on Emily Dickinson; Assembly and Club Notes, Personals.
    December 18, 1935, Vol. 12, No. 11 Inter-Club Bazaar; Assembly News; Editorial on Christmas; Coming Events; Who's Who Column; Christmas in the training schools.
    January 8, 1936, Vol. 12, No. 12 Editorial Board listed; First student-teacher groups discuss DNS curriculum; President Roosevelt's war speech; Editorial on Rudyard Kipling; Book review on "Mary Poppins" by P. L. Travers; Personals; Assembly news; Personals; Who's Who; Alumnae Notes; Coming Events.
    January 15, 1936, Vol. 12, No. 13 Public Forum Leadership course at Columbia University; Coming Events; Club Notes; Assembly News; Book review on "Valiant is the Word for Carrie" by Barry Benefield.
    January 22, 1936, Vol. 12. No. 14 Death of England's King George V; Alumnae Notes, Personals, Who's Who, Editorial on American schools; Assembly Notes.
    January 26, 1936, Vol. 12, No. 15 Italy and WW II; Assembly Notes; Popularity of Pay Collection Books; Personals, Alumnae Notes, Who's Who; Book review on "If I have Four Apples" by Josephine Lawrence.